Contact

rfordrn@yahoo.com

www.linkedin.com/in/ronford-8961686b (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Nursing Healthcare Hospice

Certifications
SMQT Certified

Honors-Awards

Nursing Consultant of the Year 2006 Road Runner Consultant Award 2007

Ron Ford

Registered Nurse at Encompass Health Dadeville

Summary

Registered Nurse with more than 23 years with experience in Regulatory Compliance, Corporate Compliance, Quality Assurance & Process Improvement. Experience with Federal Regulations pertaining to Hospice Provider Services & LTC facilities. Experienced and skillful auditor/educator with wide clinical knowledge of patient care, legal, ethical & challenging nursing services. Also have excellent computer and communication skills including experience in medical coding (ICD-10). Have gained additional leadership proficiency in nursing management and have held an Administrators License in the State of Alabama as well as other positions in management. Excel in auditing medical records, preparing reports, identifying trends, problem solving, planning and implementation of educational opportunities & team building related to those reports. Have an excellent ability to adapt to varying demands and am highly organized. A skilled technical writer of policies/procedures and processes and have a proven track record with obtainable results. Unable to relocate but willing to travel extensively for right opportunity.

Experience

Encompass Health
Registered Nurse
December 2018 - Present (1 year 9 months)

Noland Health Services, Inc.
Assistant Director Of Nursing
December 2017 - December 2018 (1 year 1 month)

Compassus

1 year

Director Of Clinical Services
December 2016 - December 2017 (1 year 1 month)

RNCM 2016 - 2017 (1 year)

Curo Health Services Inc.
RNCM
February 2015 - December 2016 (1 year 11 months)

Alabama Quality Assurance Healthcare Consultant 2013 - 2014 (1 year) QIO for Alabama

Advantage Health Care Associates LLC.

Managing Partner
2004 - 2014 (10 years)

Healthcare Consulting

SouthernCare New Beacon 5 years

Regional Quality Assurance Coordinator 2008 - 2013 (5 years)

90 offices located in 15 states throughout the U.S.

Provide comprehensive data analysis of each office in a designated region.

Coordinate office QAPI initiatives while assisting the office management teams in a performance improvement plan.

Perform ongoing comprehensive review of medical record documentation to ensure compliance with:

- *State/federal rules and regulations.
- *SouthernCare policies and procedures.
- *Discipline-specific standards of practice.

Collaborate with appropriate levels of management to facilitate a corrective action plan as related to state/federal surveys, fiscal intermediary requests and corporate compliance audits.

Provide feedback to the appropriate levels of management on medical review audits and suggestions for educational in-services to improve documentation.

Serve as a resource for patient admission appropriateness. Participate in the review, analysis and appraisal of the QAPI program including assisting with scheduling quarterly meeting, preparing agenda and meeting minutes.

Recommend policy and procedure changes and program development as appropriate. Responsible for performing Quality Assurance Summary Reports for region.

Quality Assurance Supervisor for Alabama 2009 - 2010 (1 year)

21 offices located throughout the State of Alabama

Supervise the provision of comprehensive data analysis for every office in a designated region or regions. Coordinate QAPI initiatives while assisting the office management team in a performance improvement plan.

Collaborate with the Director of Quality Assurance, Director of Education, Regional Clinical Director, Regional Clinical Coordinator and Clinical Director to facilitate a corrective action plan as related to state/federal surveys, fiscal intermediary requests and corporate compliance audits.

Provide the Director of Quality Assurance, Director of Education, Regional Clinical Director, Regional Clinical Coordinator and Clinical Director with feedback on medical review audits and suggestions for educational in-services to improve documentation.

Collaborate with the director of education to provide educational needs to individual offices in the designated region/regions. Provide education to the individual offices in the designated region/regions.

Serve as a resource for patient admission appropriateness.

Participate in the review, analysis and appraisal of the QAPI program including assisting with scheduling quarterly meetings, preparing agenda and meeting minutes. Recommend policy and procedure changes and program development as appropriate.

Responsible for performing Quality Assurance Summary Reports for region.

Performance Improvement/Education Specialist 2008 - 2009 (1 year)

90 offices located in 15 states throughout the U.S.

The PI/Education Specialist is responsible for the promotion, coordination, and implementation of staff development and performance improvement activities.

Promote staff retention, reduces risk exposure, and enhances employee competencies through staff training initiatives. Conduct annual corporate compliance reviews to monitor compliance with Federal, State and Company guidelines. Plan educational programs for personnel in consultation with Director Education and the Regional management team.

Conduct educational needs assessment of personnel on an ongoing basis. Implement and monitors the adherence to regional and corporate training initiatives. Develop and conducts educational programs that are location specific, but ensures that the programs meet and are consistent with the administrative and clinical policies of the company. Maintain records of all data related to educational activities.

Establish a system for the storage of educational records which assures confidentiality and allows for effective retrieval. Coordinate with the Program Development Specialist in the awarding of certificates or written statements verifying an individual's attendance and completion of an educational activity. Review participant evaluations of educational programs. Participate in the continuous quality improvement activities of the locations.

Ensure confidentiality of employee records/information. Attend operational meetings and phone conferences to enhance team communication, coordination of services, and professional knowledge.

Complete reports and any required paperwork in a timely fashion to ensure agency objectives.

HMR Veterans Services, Inc. Regional Nurse Consultant 2004 - 2008 (4 years) 900+ Beds in 4 States

Coordinate and assist LTC Facilities with specialized clinical needs of Operations, Nursing Services, and the Accounting Department. Assist with implementing tools to monitor and evaluate the quality of care given at the facilities.

Provide assistance to LTC facilities with interviewing clinical/nursing candidates if requested. Responsible for coordinating clinical and or nursing committees (to include Peer Review) as needed. Oversee the company Medical Records Review and appeal protocol to assure compliance.

Responsible for the auditing of Medicare resident's MDS and Care Plans.

Responsible for all specialized clinical training to include PPS/MDS training programs and protocols. Coordinate and review "My Innerview" and other Quality Indicator reports for accuracy on a monthly basis.

Provide LTC facilities with updated information regarding survey process. Encourage networking among the facilities. Maintain effective relationships with Directors of Nursing and Administrators through periodic meetings and facility visits. Assist with the coordinating and planning of the Director of Nursing new employee orientations and regular meetings throughout the year.

State of Alabama LTC/Complaint Surveyor 1998 - 2004 (6 years)

Education

Troy University
Registered Nursing/Registered Nurse

Troy University
Registered Nursing/Registered Nurse

University of Maryland College Park

John Patterson Technical College